Charles Trantanella Papers on Greek Life at Tufts MS239
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Charles Trantanella Papers on Greek Life at Tufts
circa 2010 -- 2022
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS239
2 Linear Feet
1 Volumes
This collection contains research notes and materials compiled and used by Charles Trantanella to write "Brown and Blue and Greek: A history of fraternities and sororities at Tufts University."
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Trantanella, 2017, accession MS-2018-028.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in received order, which is largely by Greek organization and year. Original folder titles were maintained.
Content Description
This collection contains research notes and materials compiled and used by Charles Trantanella to write "Brown and Blue and Greek: A history of fraternities, sororities, and early student organizations at Tufts University." Material includes handwritten and typed notes as well as photocopied archival material and photographs, and is largely arranged by Greek organization and year, beginning in the 1850s and dating through 2015. Original folder titles were maintained. The collection also contains a copy of the published book, as well as reference copies made from archival material related to Tufts fraternal organizations at other institutions, such as the American Jewish Historical Society and the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
Existence and Location of Originals
American Jewish Historical Society. New York, New York. University of Illinois Archives. Urbana, Illinois.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Joseph Trantanella (1967- ) earned his bachelor of science degree in Electrical Engineering at Tufts University in 1989. He is the author of Brown and Blue and Greek: A history of fraternities, sororities, and early student organizations at Tufts University (2017). Charles Joseph Trantanella was born in Massachussetts in 1967 to Sheilagh Trantanella and the late Charles Trantanella, Jr. He attended Tufts University, where he was a part of the Sigma Nu fraternity as well as the Men's Cross-Country team, and where he met his wife, Valerie Ruth Hodgkin. After graduating Tufts in 1989, he received a M.S. and PhD in Electrical Engineering at the University of Arizona. In August 2010, Trantanella started writing a book that would look at the history of the fifty-five fraternity and sorority organizations that have existed at Tufts University since the school's founding. He was inspired by newly digitized school records, specifically old photographs, on the Tufts website. Trantanella wanted to focus on student life, an area he felt was neglected in existing histories of Tufts. For his book, he interviewed over 150 Tufts alumni and professors, spoke to 50 other national organizations, and did archival research in Digital Collections and Archives at Tufts University. Brown and Blue and Greek: A history of fraternities, sororities, and early student organizations at Tufts University was published in August 2017. Trantanella lives in Westford, MA with his wife and two children. He is an electrical engineer in Chelmsford, MA.
Greek letter societies; Fraternities; Sororities; Tufts University -- History; University history
- Charles Trantanella Papers on Greek Life at Tufts, circa 2010 -- 2022; MS239.001; 2 Linear Feet; 1 Volumes
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order, which is largely by Greek organization and year. Original folder titles were maintained.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  This collection contains research notes and materials compiled and used by Charles Trantanella to write "Brown and Blue and Greek: A history of fraternities, sororities, and early student organizations at Tufts University." Material includes handwritten and typed notes as well as photocopied archival material and photographs, and is largely arranged by Greek organization and year, beginning in the 1850s and dating through 2015. Original folder titles were maintained. The collection also contains a copy of the published book, as well as reference copies made from archival material related to Tufts fraternal organizations at other institutions, such as the American Jewish Historical Society and the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
  - Mathetican [sic] Society, Full Moon Club, Order of Coffee Pot, Zetagathean, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Zeta Psi 1855, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Theta Delta Chi 1856, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Theta Delta Chi #2, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Delta Upsilon 1886, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Engineers Fraternity 1890-94, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Delta Tau Delta 1889, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Heth Aleph Res 1891, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Alpha Tau Omega 1893, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - ATO-A 41/95/1 Visitation File 1967-74, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - ATO-A 41/90/1 High Council Minutes 1973-74, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - ATO-A 41/95/1 Correspondence 1970-75, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Alpha Tau Omega 1934 - Present, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Sigma Tau Alpha / Phi Mu Delta 1906, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Commons Club / Delta Phi Sigma / Alpha Kappa Pi / Alpha Sigma Phi 1908-1970, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - CC / Delta Phi Sigma / Alpha Kappa Pi / Alpha Sigma Phi 1970-92, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Delta / Sigma Nu 1913, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Sigma Nu Ted Snowe Archives, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi / Zeta Beta Tau 1916, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi - AJHS Archives - 1916 to 1921, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi - AJHS Archives - 1921 to 1928, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi - AJHS Archives - 1929 to 1934, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi - AJHS Archives - 1935 to 1936, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi - AJHS Archives - 1937 to 1944, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Epsilon Pi - AJHS Archives - 1945 to 1957, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - JAN Rosenbach - AFSC Files, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Tau Epsilon Phi 1917-1931, 1958-1964, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Beta Tau 1919 / Beta Kappa 1925 / Beta Chi 1954 / Theta Chi 1957, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Beta Delta (Pi Lambda Phi) 1921-1934? [sic], circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Sigma Omega Psi 1922-1970 / Alpha Epsilon Pi 1976-82 / Nichols 1983 - present, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Phi Sigma Kappa 1957-1976 Theta Delta Theta 1952-1957, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Psi Upsilon 1981-1992, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Sigma Phi Epsilon 1985 / Pi Rho Omega 1983? [sic], circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Alpha Phi Delta 1996-2004, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Hazing, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Tufts Administrator Interviews, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00036; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Other Greek Org. looking at Tufts, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00037; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Tufts Fraternity History Articles Globe, Daily, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00038; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Tufts becomes Co-ed, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00039; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Alpha Delta Sigma / Delta Sigma / Alpha Omicron Pi 1895, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.001.00040; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Alpha Kappa Gamma / Chi Omega 1895, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Tau Epsilon Sigma / Alpha Xi Delta / Alethea 1896, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Delphoi, Delta Kappa Phi 1912?, Sigma Kappa 1913, Thalia, circa 2010 -- 2022; MS239.001.002.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
    Includes a letter of apology from Sigma Kappa to Terrie Williams Schachter, apologizing for its treatment of her pledge in 1956. The national organization did not allow the pledge of black students at the time and as a result the Tufts chapter lost its charter.
  - Phi Sigma Sigma 1918, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Alpha Phi 1978, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Delta Zeta 1956, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Kappa Alpha Theta, Alpha Gamma Delta 2013, 2015, 2010-2017; MS239.001.002.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - BGLO's, Tufts Info (General), circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha: [Chapters] Sigma - 1915, Rho Nu - 1989, both for Tufts, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Omega Psi Phi: [Chapter] Gamma - 1916, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Delta Sigma Theta: [Chapters] Iota - 1921, Xi Tau - 1980, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Alpha Kappa Alpha - Epsilon (1924), circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Kappa Alpha Psi: [Chapters] Chi (1924), Theta Iota (1975), circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Phi Beta Sigma, Beta Alpha, 1955 / Zeta Phi Beta, Theta Alpha, 1933, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Sigma Gamma Rho - Kappa Nu (1984), circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Lambda Pi Chi - Nu Chapter (1999), circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Delta Lambda Phi, Alpha Chi, 2001, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Delta Psi Sigma (Asian Sorority) - Boston 2002, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Latino/Latina: Lambda Upsilon Lambda 1993, Alpha Rho Lambda 1996, Omega Phi Beta 1997-2002, Sigma Lambda Upsilon (2001), circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Mayoralty History, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Anti-Frat, Discriminatory Clause Fight, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - ATO-A 41/90/10 Membership Clause File Tufts 1961-65, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Co-ed Decision 1992 History IGC Reform 1987-92, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - General Tufts History, circa 2010 -- 2017; MS239.001.002.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2)
  - Brown and Blue and Greek: A history of fraternities, sororities, and early student organizations at Tufts University, 2017; MS239.001.003; 1 Volumes (Volume 3)
    This is a copy of Charles Trantanella's published book.